Alice Morgan Wright Papers, 1873-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Alice Morgan Wright papers
1873-1994
Wright, Alice Morgan
MS 176
11 boxes (4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Sculptor, Suffragist, Animal welfare advocate. Papers include biographical material, correspondence, writings, postcards, scrapbooks, artwork and photographs of her work as a sculptor; subject files, and memorabilia. Wright's career as a sculptor and her activism are well-documented; personal material is more fragmentary. Topics include art, women's suffrage, women's rights, women companions, birth control, world peace, and animal welfare. Notable correspondents include Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley, Edith J. Goode (Wright's lifelong partner), and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.
Alice Morgan Wright, sculptor, suffragist, and animal welfare advocate, the daughter of Henry Romeyn Wright, a prosperous wholesale grocer, and Emma Jane Morgan, was born on October 10, 1881, in Albany, New York. She attended the St. Agnes School in Albany (now the Doane Stuart School) and then graduated from Smith College in 1904.
Wright worked for the Collegiate Equal Suffrage League and began studying sculpture at the Art Student League in New York City. In 1909 the League awarded her both the Gutzon Borglum and the Augustus Saint-Gaudens prizes for her outstanding art work. She went on to study art at the Académie des Beaux-Arts and at the Académie Colarossi in Paris. While in Europe, Wright involved herself in both the British and French suffrage movements. She organized a meeting in Paris at which English suffragist Emmeline Pankhurst spoke in 1910 and arranged for Pankhurst to make an appearance in Albany during her tour of the United States in 1911.
During a suffrage demonstration, Wright was arrested and spent two months in London's Holloway Gaol. During this time she modeled a small bust of Emmeline Pankhurst, her prison-mate, with art supplies she had smuggled into the prison. When she returned to Paris she organized a petition drive demanding the release of jailed British suffragists. By 1913 Wright's art work had won several prizes, and had been exhibited in New York, Paris, and London. After returning home in 1914, she became the recording secretary of the New York State Women's Suffrage Party, and only returned full time to her sculpture after the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment.
Wright's lifelong companion was Edith J. Goode, whom she met at Smith, and together they worked tirelessly for peace and justice. Wright's love of animals increasingly drew her to the cause of animal protection, and although she was heralded as one of the leading young American sculptors, art increasingly took a backseat to her reform activities. By 1945 she was devoting all her time to the cause, founding the National Humane Education Association, and working with various other animal protection organizations. Russell Sage College awarded her an honorary degree in 1947. Wright died in Albany at the age of 93, on April 8, 1975.
The Alice Morgan Wright Papers include biographical material, correspondence, writings, postcards, scrapbooks, artwork and photographs of her work as a sculptor; subject files, and memorabilia. Wright's career as a sculptor and her activism are well-documented; personal material is more fragmentary. Topics include art, women's suffrage, women's rights, women companions, birth control, world peace, animal welfare, the International Police Force and the United Nations, and Navajo Indians. Her postcards provide a vivid and interesting account of Wright's travels, especially her years as an art student in Paris. Also included are reminiscences of the Pankhursts and of Wright's confinement in Holloway Gaol where she spent two months after her arrest at a suffrage demonstration in England.
Notable correspondents include Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley, Edith J. Goode (Wright's lifelong partner), and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.
This collection is organized into six series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1873-1990)
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1909-78)
SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS (1903-75)
SERIES IV. ARTWORK (1907-78)
SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES (1912-94)
SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS (1893-1970s)
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Most of Alice Morgan Wright's papers were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by her cousin Elinor Wright Fleming (Mrs. Clark M. Fleming) in 1980. Wright herself had sent small increments earlier. Photographs of Smith College, originally passed on to Ruth Sharp from the estate of Alice Morgan Wright, were sent to President Thomas Mendenhall in 1965 by Ruth and Lauriston Sharp. In 1998 Ann Lee O'Connell Anderson '55 and Albert G. Anderson donated a watercolor painting of an unidentified young woman, done by Wright in 1916. Betsy Fahlman donated additional materials pertaining to Wright's artwork in 1998. Dorcas MacClintock gave biographical materials, including Betsy Fahlman's definitive work on Wright's sculpture, in 2003.
Search Terms
Animal welfare--History--Sources; Art--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Female friendship--History--Sources; Humane education--History--Sources; Paris (France)--Description and travel--Sources; Sculptors--United States--Biography--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Suffragists--Great Britain--History--Sources; Suffragists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women sculptors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Great Britain--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.); New York State Woman Suffrage Party; Women's Party (Great Britain); Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928; Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline, 1867-; Whitehouse, Vira Boarman, 1875-; Wright, Alice Morgan, 1881-1975
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional papers pertaining to Alice Morgan Wright are housed at the Albany Institute of History and Art (125 Washington Avenue, Albany, New York).
Sketches Wright made of classmates at Smith are present in the student files in the Smith College Archives. Artwork by Wright can be seen around the Smith College campus: sculpture in Alumnae Gym; Doleman plaque on College Hall; and Seelye plaque on John M. Greene porch. Materials regarding the National Humane Education Society can be found in the Miscellaneous Organizations Collection of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Bibliography
Additional biographical information can be found in Notable American women, 1607-1950; a biographical dictionary. Edward T. James, editor. Janet Wilson James, associate editor. Paul S. Boyer, assistant editor. (Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1971- )
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1873-1990
  [See also SERIES IV. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES - WLG 1838 and WLG 1874 commemorative verse and writings]
  This series contains articles, clippings, and notes by and about Wright. It also contains her telephone and address books. Materials pertaining to her education at Smith College, such as notebooks, sketchbooks, correspondence and the Ivy Oration by Wright, are also included. Awards and citations, including the honorary degree she received from Russell Sage College in 1947, speeches, memorabilia, and miscellaneous family material are contained in this series. Also present are her obituaries, her will, and the instructions to its executors.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1909-78
  Correspondence includes letters from Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, and Mary E. Woolley. Postcards provide a vivid and interesting account of Wright's travels, especially her years as an art student in Paris, and include correspondence between Edith J. Goode, Wright's lifelong partner, and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.
- SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS 1903-75
  Wright's scrapbooks contain clippings pertaining to subjects that were of great interest to her. The Whiteface Mountain scrapbook focuses on current affairs. She devoted one scrapbook entirely to art clippings (1903-75, n.d.) and another to theatre programs and pictures (1904, n.d.). This series also includes a scrapbook entitled "For Alice Morgan Wright - A Friend of Pussy-Cats" (n.d.) containing animal pictures and poems that was probably compiled by a friend and gifted to Wright.
- SERIES IV. ARTWORK 1907-78
  This series contains Wrights artwork and related materials. It also includes the Mary Augusta Jordan medal presented to Wright; two metal plates for the L. Clarke Seelye bas relief done by her; various sketches and drawings - including those done for greeting cards for the National Humane Education Society; and the bookplate done for the Anna Cutler Fund, Smith College Library. The series also contains verse by Wright, clippings and writings about her artwork, exhibit catalogues and materials, and original artwork by others, including works by Shirley Thomson.
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES 1912-94
  The subject files, like Wright's scrapbooks, contain materials pertaining to subjects that were of interest to her and with which she was actively involved. This series includes materials regarding animal protection; birth control; women's rights; the International Police Force and the United Nations; Navajo Indians; and Suffrage, including memorabilia, such as a knife and a hunger strike medal, of the time Wright spent in confinement in Holloway Gaol after her arrest at a suffrage demonstration in England.
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS 1893-1970s
  This series contains portraits of Wright; and photographs of her with friends, animals, and her artwork. There are photographs pertaining to Smith College, including photographs of John M. Greene, and of Wright's classmates. The series also contains a sub series devoted entirely to photographs of Wright's artwork - contact prints of her artwork and studio, bas relief (including the one of L. Clarke Seelye), busts, and sculpture. Another sub series contains various negatives.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, clippings, and notes by and about A.M.W
    - General, 1918-90, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Alice Morgan Wright (1881-1975)," by Marla Frances Wagshal, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Telephone and address books (5) (Box 1)
  - Index cards with addresses (Box 1)
  - Education: Smith College
    - Notebook, correspondence and ivy oration by AMW, 1903-63, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Verses," notebook with notes and sketches, undated (Box 2)
    - "A. Morg. Wright," sketchbook with notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Awards and citations
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-71, undated, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Russell Sage College Honorary Degree, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia, 1908-53, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries, 1967-75 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Will and instructions to executors, 1954-67 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous family material, 1873-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Miscellaneous correspondence with and regarding family, 1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A-Z (includes Florence E. Allen, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Alice Paul, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley), 1910-78, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Balch, Emily Greene, 1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Benoit, Maria. 1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bispham, David, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gobinot, B., 1946, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Grierson, Margaret S. and Marine Leland (includes letters to Edith Goode), 1947-63, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Guilbert, Yvette, 1917, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lefaucheux, Marie Helene, 1949-50 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lutz, Bertha, 1947-52, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mehta, Shrimati Hansa, 1948-53 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Menon (Pandit), Vijaya Lakshmi, 1949-62, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1911-13 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline, 1912, 1948-52 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick, 1948-57 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Shepard, Edith, 1909-13, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Undset, Sigrid, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Whitehouse, Vira B., 1918-20 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified, 1912-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Business, 1910-51 (includes Ruth Benedict) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Postcards
    - From AMW to the Wright family, 1908-27, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - From AMW to parents and others, 1909-31, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - To AMW, circa 1905-31, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified, 1910-30, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS
  - Whiteface Mountain Amendment (1), 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Whiteface Mountain Amendment (2), 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Art clippings, 1903-75, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Theatre programs and pictures, 1904, undated (Box 5)
  - "For Alice Morgan Wright - A Friend of Pussy-Cats," undated (Box 6)
- SERIES IV. ARTWORK
  - "Pastorale" bas relief; bronze medal for fifty years of service at the College of the City of New York, 1907; Mary Augusta Jordan medal; 2 metal plates for the L. Clarke Seelye bas relief (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sketches and drawings (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Elizabeth Edmond," sketchbook with notes, undated (Box 7)
  - Betsy Fahlman (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1974-75 (Box 7)
    - "Catalogue of works of sculpture contained in the studio of Alice Morgan Wright (1881-1975)," 1975 (Box 7)
    - "Sculpture and Suffrage: The Art and Life of Alice Morgan Wright, 1881-1975," catalogue of exhibition at Albany Institute of Art, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Drawings, mostly greeting cards, for National Humane Education Society, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bookplate done for Anna Cutler Fund, Smith College Library, undated (Box 7)
  - Clippings, 1911-75, undated, [see also SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS] (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Exhibit catalogues and materials, 1915-78, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1910-75, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Original artwork by others, including works by Shirley Thomson, 1912-39, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Verse by Alice Morgan Wright, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES
  - Animal protection
    - Correspondence, 1952-67, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Humane Society of the United States, 1954-79 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-66, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - National Humane Education Society, 1949-94, undated, [see also Miscellaneous file above] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - UNESCO and UN, 1950-59, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Birth control: correspondence (letters from Margaret Sanger, others at Planned Parenthood, and A. H. Askanasy), 1948-61, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Women's rights, 1948-50, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - International Police Force and UN, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Navajo Indians, Toadlena, N.M., 1932-34, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Suffrage
    - Prison in England
      - Notes, writings, and memorabilia, 1912, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence: letters from, and visiting cards of, French associates, 1912, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Mementos: hunger strike medal and knife, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Clippings, 1912-17, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915-16, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Parade New York, Oct 1917: clippings (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - United Nations: reports and "Christmas Message" by AMW, 1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Alice Morgan Wright, 1893- circa 1970s, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - AMW and others: art classes, studio, and with animals, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Others: studio, miscellaneous, and unidentified, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - AMW and a friend: glass negatives, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Smith College
    - John M. Greene and others, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Classmates from scrapbook, n.d. circa 1902-07 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Artwork
    - Contact prints of artwork and studio, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Bas reliefs, undated (Seelye circa 1914; Doleman circa 1922) (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Busts, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Sculpture, undated (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - Artwork by others, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Negatives
    - AMW in New York State Suffrage Party booth, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Artwork and studio, n.d. circa 1910-13 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
    - Friends and animals, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS (Flat file)
  - Art folio of original drawings and sketches by Alice Morgan Wright (Box 12)
  - Certificate from the Women's Social and Political Union, signed by Emmeline Pankhurst (Map-case Flat file)
  - "Clacton's Welcome to Released Suffragettes": clipping, 4 May 1912 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Suffrage Parade: clipping, 4 Nov 1917 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Art show for cause of suffrage: poster from New York Tribune 10 Oct 1915 (Map-case Flat file)